Suchismit Mahapatra

RESEARCH SCIENTIST · (MACHINE LEARNING | DEEP LEARNING

Amobee Research, Redwood City, CA 94063

□716-435-8865 | ☑ suchismi@buffalo.edu | 备 https://schrilax.github.io/ | 📠 suchismit | 🛗 schrilaxs | 📓 suchismit

About Me

I am a Research Scientist with Amobee, applying different Machine/Deep Learning and NLP techniques to solve related problems. I completed my PhD with the Machine Learning & Data Science Research group at University of Buffalo. I have 7+ years of research and 5 years of developer experience during which I have been exposed and worked on a variety of problems.

Research Interests __

My research focuses on designing and implementing novel algorithms which enable large-scale learning and includes:

- Machine/Deep Learning
- Natural Language Processing (NLP)

- Deep Graph/Geometric Learning
- Nonlinear/Distributed Optimization

Academic Background _____

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

April 2012 - June 2018

Buffalo, NY

- Topic: Scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods for streaming data.
- · Advisors: Varun Chandola, Nils Napp & Jaroslaw Zola | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 (Transcript)

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

September 2010 - June 2012

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

- Topic: A Cold Start Recommendation System Using Item Correlation and User Similarity. 🔼
- Advisor: Rohini Srihari | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 | Department rank: 1 out of 555 (Transcript)

National Institute of Technology, Rourkela

Rourkela, India

August 2001 - May 2005

B.Tech. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

• Specialization: Discrete Mathematics and Algorithms

• Cumulative Score: 77% (First class with Honors)(Transcript) | Joint Entrance Exam Rank 22 out of 400,000

Honors _

| 2021 | Became a reviewer for EMNLP 2021, ACL 2021 and NeurIPS 2021. | Sunnyvale, CA |
|------|---|-----------------|
| 2020 | Became a reviewer for ICML 2021 and ICLR 2021. | Sunnyvale, CA |
| 2020 | Was invited to and attended the prestigious Theory of Reinforcement Learning program. | Berkeley, CA |
| 2019 | Became a reviewer for ICML 2020. | Palo Alto, CA |
| 2019 | Was invited to and attended the prestigious Foundations of Deep Learning program. | Berkeley, CA |
| 2017 | Won a NSF Junior Researcher Award to attend CBMS Conference on Sparse Recovery. | Las Cruces, NM |
| 2016 | Became a NVIDIA GPU Educator. | Santa Clara, CA |
| 2015 | Won a NSF Student Travel Award to attend IEEE Big Data 2015. | Santa Clara, CA |
| 2013 | Won a rare Research Assistant-ship covering my second year as a Masters student. | Buffalo, NY |

Skills & Proficiencies _____

Python | PyTorch | C/C++ | TensorFlow | Apache MapReduce | Scala | CUDA | Hive

Research Experience _____

Amobee Research

SCIENTIST I

Redwood City, CA

March 2020 - Present

- Developed a novel bidding strategy based on Win Price (WP) estimation
 - Developed and productionized a novel bidding strategy using nonlinear ML based approaches for estimating WP.
- Built a Factorization Machine (FM/FFM) based ML pipeline for usage in production
 - Led efforts to build a FM/FFM based ML pipeline using a novel sparse matrix formulation that can handle high modality features.
- Incorporating user embeddings into existing ML/DL models to improve performance
 - Trained BERT/GAN based generative models to construct user embeddings for usage by our existing models.

Criteo Research Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST

July 2018 - December 2019

- Improve Click-through and Sales prediction
 - Enhanced existing production Click-through and Sales prediction pipeline using nonlinear ML techniques. Improved stability of our new models significantly from +50% to +5%. A/B test using new models resulted in +3-6% uplift in long-term RexT on all platforms.
- Theoretical aspects on Deep Learning (working with Noureddine El Karoui)
 - Working towards understanding kernel and manifold specific aspects of theoretical deep learning.
- Resolving the posterior-collapse issue in Seq2Seq learning
 - Developed a quantization based approach towards resolving the posterior-collapse issue. 🔼

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

January 2018 - May 2018

- RESEARCH ASSISTANT
- Parallelized Hierarchical Clustering (worked with Haimonti Dutta)
- Worked towards developing a novel parallel hierarchical clustering algorithm using activization strategies.
- Kernel Manifold Learning (worked with Varun Chandola)
- Developed novel Manifold Learning techniques motivated from Gaussian Processes. 🔀

Criteo Research Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

September 2017 - December 2017

• Efficient Domain Adaptation (worked with Suju Rajan)

- Understanding how to efficiently deal with the Domain Adaptation problem via Optimal Transportation.

Criteo Research Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Cross-domain Query-Product (QP) modeling using Adversarial Transfer Learning (worked with Suju Rajan)
 - Developed a robust QP model across retailer domains using Adversarial Transfer Learning.

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

January 2017 - May 2017

May 2017 - August 2017

• Representation learning via DL/NLSDR methods (worked with Varun Chandola / Nils Napp / Jaroslaw Zola)

- Interpreting complex nonlinear processes using DL/NLSDR methods. 🔁 🛗 🛗

BD Biosciences San Jose, CA

MACHINE LEARNING ALGORITHM DESIGN INTERN

June 2016 - August 2016

June 2013 - December 2015

- Fast Clustering of Flow Cytometry (FC) data
 - Upscaled BD's clustering framework for high dimensional FC data upto ~16x. 🔼 🚨

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction (worked with Varun Chandola / Jaroslaw Zola / Nils Napp)
- Developed scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods in a streaming setting. 🔼
- Social Network Modeling (worked with Varun Chandola)
 - Developed the xKPGM model for social network modeling.
- Volcanic Flow Prediction (worked with Abani Patra / Varun Chandola / Paul Bauman)
 - Developed a novel Gaussian Process based model for prediction of volcanic flow using GPUs.

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

Lacalization via Entrany Daduction (worked with Daba

June 2011 - August 2012

- Localization via Entropy Reduction (worked with Robert Platt)
 - Developed a novel active localization technique via sequential reduction of entropy using OpenRAVE/ROS. 🔼 🛗

Publications

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- 1. Interpretable Graph Similarity Computation via Optimal Assignment of Stacked GCN Layers. Khoa Doan, Saurav Manchanda, **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Chandan Reddy. (To appear in SIGIR 2021)
- 2. Discretized Bottleneck in VAE: Posterior-Collapse-Free Sequence-to-Sequence Learning. Yang Zhao, Ping Yu, **Suchismit Mahapatra**, Qinliang Su and Changyou Chen. 2020 (Under submission)
- 3. Learning Manifolds from Non-stationary Streaming Data. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. 2019 (Preprint available in arXiv)
- 4. S-Isomap++: Multi Manifold Learning from Streaming Data. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. Proceedings of 5th IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2017
- 5. Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. Suchismit Mahapatra, Frank Schoeneman, Varun Chan-

6. Modeling Graphs Using a Mixture of Kronecker Models. **Suchismit Mahapatra** and Varun Chandola. Proceedings of the 3rd IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2015.

Additional Certifications/Projects

- NLP certification from NVIDIA Deep Learning Institute
- Machine Learning course offered by Stanford under Andrew Ng
- Optimization/Mathematics/ML courses offered by Coursera D
 D
 L
 <a href="Li
- Developed ElGooG A search engine using ~100000 TREC documents as corpus (won the NTipS 2010 competition) 🚨

Teaching _

- Taught a course on Classification and Decision Trees [Q4 2018, Q2 2019, Q4 2019] while at Criteo Research.
- Taught a course on Generative Models [Q2 2019, Q4 2019] while at Criteo Research.

Seminar/Symposia _

| 2017 | S-Isomap++: Multi Manifold Learning from Streaming Data. (IEEE Big Data 2017) 🔼 | Boston, NY |
|------|--|-----------------|
| 2017 | Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. (SIAM SDM 2017) 🔼 | Houston, TX |
| 2016 | Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. (UB Computer Science Mixer) 🕒 | Buffalo, NY |
| 2016 | Fast Clustering of Flow Cytometry Data via Adaptive Mean Shift. (BD Biosciences) 🚨 🔼 | San Jose, CA |
| 2015 | Modeling Graphs Using a Mixture of Kronecker Models. (IEEE Big Data 2015) 🔼 | Santa Clara, CA |
| 2012 | Entropy-based localization framework for localizing known objects. (NEMS 2012) 🛗 | Bedford, MA |